<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Tertium Quid: post-modern magical consciousness</title><link>http://example.org/articles/</link><description>Recent content on Tertium Quid: post-modern magical consciousness</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 04 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://example.org/articles/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Newthought Test</title><link>http://example.org/articles/test-newthought/</link><pubDate>Tue, 04 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://example.org/articles/test-newthought/</guid><description>This is a test for Hugo’s newthought shortcode.
Newthought should appear styled here .</description></item><item><title>scientific method</title><link>http://example.org/articles/scientific_method/</link><pubDate>Wed, 28 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://example.org/articles/scientific_method/</guid><description>This is a test for newthought in Hugo the text would carry
In her review of a book by Henry Cowles on the history of the scientific method,(1) (1)Henry M. Cowles, The Scientific Method: An Evolution of Thinking from Darwin to Dewey Jessica Riskin recounts that the word “scientist” was coined in 1834 as a joke by William Whewell in his “excruciatingly patronizing” review of Mary Somerville’s book On the Connexion of the Physical Sciences.</description></item><item><title>spiritual frameworks</title><link>http://example.org/articles/spiritual_frameworks/</link><pubDate>Wed, 28 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://example.org/articles/spiritual_frameworks/</guid><description>&amp;ldquo;The most important and exceedingly difficult task of our time is to work on the construction of a new idea of reality.&amp;rdquo;
&amp;mdash; Wolfgang Pauli
Is the world, reality, very, very different from what most of us have been taught through modern science? Could non-physical properties (mind, spirit, or other)(1) (1)Provisionally interchangeable terms include mind, spirit, Tao, be as fundamental as charge or mass? Can ancient traditions and mystical perspectives contribute to a more complete picture of the way the universe really is than our current physicalist conception?</description></item><item><title>classical worldview</title><link>http://example.org/articles/classical_worldview/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://example.org/articles/classical_worldview/</guid><description>The term &amp;ldquo;classical worldview&amp;rdquo; is broadly used to describe the scientific description of the world that began with Greek philosophers and reached its zenith in the 19th century. It was conceived 2,500 years ago as a rational replacement of myths about gods who controlled the world by imposing their whims through acts of nature they caused. As Morris Kline put it:
&amp;ldquo;The Greek intellectuals adopted a totally new attitude toward nature.</description></item><item><title>full humanness</title><link>http://example.org/articles/full_humanness/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://example.org/articles/full_humanness/</guid><description>A.H. Maslow coined a number of terms that have come into common parlance beyond academic psychology , including &amp;ldquo;hierarchy of needs&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;self-actualization&amp;rdquo;, and &amp;ldquo;peak experience&amp;rdquo;. In his last book, The Farther Reaches of Human Nature, Maslow uses the term &amp;ldquo;full humanness&amp;rdquo; to describe psychologically healthy and mature people&amp;ndash; those who are self-actualized and beyond. But what defines a self-actualized person? And what lies beyond self-actualization?
Maslow understood the inherent difficulty of explicitly answering such subjective questions.</description></item><item><title>fusion illusion</title><link>http://example.org/articles/fusion_illusion/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://example.org/articles/fusion_illusion/</guid><description>“There is potential in fusion to revolutionize our world and to change all of the options that are in front of us and provide the world with abundant and clean energy without the harmful emissions of traditional energy sources.”
— John Kerry, Special Presidential Envoy for Climate, 2023
Hopes that fusion power will save us from the looming crises of global warming appear to be even stronger now than they were in 1954 when Lewis Strauss— then chairman of the Atomic Energy Commission, and in apparent reference to fusion power— infamously declared that nuclear power would one day be too cheap to meter.</description></item><item><title>life-organizing principles</title><link>http://example.org/articles/life_organizing_principles/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://example.org/articles/life_organizing_principles/</guid><description>Would that more people followed these seemingly simple principles(1) (1)Summarized from the works of Alice Bailey, particularly A Treatise on White Magic. Above all, practice harmlessness # Hold no harmful thoughts. Express no harmful words. Maintain positive harmlessness and constant watchfulness. Engage in no harmful action. Avoid negative harmlessness and tolerance through avoidance. Desire nothing for your separated self # Practice and strive for simplicity. Reject materialism. Eliminate possessiveness and self-reference.</description></item><item><title>Phoenix Affirmations</title><link>http://example.org/articles/phoenix_affirmations/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://example.org/articles/phoenix_affirmations/</guid><description>Christianity has gone through a number of significant metamorphoses over the last two millennia, some of them radical enough to permanently change the nature of the West&amp;rsquo;s foremost religion. Another radical change is beginning to swell through the sea of mainstream Christianity as increasing numbers of thoughtful Christians challenge the prevailing doctrines of separation and exclusion, preferring instead to focus on the personal change that comes from a sincere attempt to emulate the life of Jesus.</description></item><item><title>physicalism</title><link>http://example.org/articles/physicalism/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://example.org/articles/physicalism/</guid><description>“The most important and exceedingly difficult task of our time is to work on the construction of a new idea of reality.”
— Wolfgang Pauli
Almost a century after the initial discoveries of the quantum nature of matter, and many decades after they were confirmed beyond serious question, even many well-educated people do not know that quantum physics appears to have upended a conception of reality that has been in place since the 17th century.</description></item><item><title>Thomas Nagel</title><link>http://example.org/articles/thomas_nagel/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://example.org/articles/thomas_nagel/</guid><description>Thomas Nagel is a leading and articulate critic of reductionist materialism, the dominant worldview in modern secular society. In his 2012 Mind &amp;amp; Cosmos: Why the Neo-Darwinian Conception of Nature is Almost Certainly Wrong, Nagel argues that we need a new, radically different narrative from the dominant scientistic worldview of reductive materialism, contrasting it against theism. Although he takes a relatively broad brush to the concept of theism, he acknowledges that belief in God as fundamental to the universe remains a major alternative to the materialist worldview.</description></item><item><title>uncivilization</title><link>http://example.org/articles/dark_mountain/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://example.org/articles/dark_mountain/</guid><description>When will industrial civilization begin to decline? How long before it is considered an historical relic? Paul Kingsnorth and Dougald Hine&amp;rsquo;s 2009 essay Uncivilization, The Dark Mountain Manifesto argues that our industrial civilization faces a progressive and inevitable decline. Civilizations throughout history have come and gone, they point out, and ours will be no different. Indeed, Kingsnorth and Hine believe that decline has already begun. Critical resource depletion, exploding world population, global warming: any one of them could lead to a system failure; together they virtually guarantee it.</description></item></channel></rss>